ACTWU Memorabilia Collection 5619 MB
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU Memorabilia Collection
1913-1989
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
5619 MB
7.72 cubic feet
7.7 linear ft.
Memorabilia.
This collection is made up of some ACTWU and ILGWU memorabilia found at the UNITE offices.
5675115
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 12, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 21, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes. Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals. Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants. Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable. During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Scope and Contents
This collection is made up of some ACTWU and ILGWU memorabilia found at the UNITE offices.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5619: ACWA Records 5619 AV: ACTWU Audio-Visual Materials 5619 C-S MB: ACTWU President Jack Sheinkman Additional Books, Memorabilia, and Files 5619 F: ACTWU Motion Picture Films 5619 G: ACTWU Graphics 5619 mf: ACWA Records Parts 1-3 on Microfilm 5619 OH: ACWA Oral History Project Records 5619 P: ACTWU Photographs 5619 PUBS: ACTWU Publications 5619/001: ACTWU Collective Bargaining Agreements 5619/002: ACWA Education Department Records 5619/003: ACWA Sidney Hillman Scrapbooks 5619/004: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Files 5619/004 fiche: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Speeches on Microfiche 5619/005: ACWA Bessie Hillman Papers 5619/006: ACTWU Executive Vice-President's Office Files 5619/007: ACTWU Organizing Department Files 5619/008: ACWA Rieve-Pollock Foundation Files 5619/009: ACTWU Operations Department Sidney Hillman Awards Files 5619/010: ACWA Jacob Potofsky files 5619/011: ACTWU Southern Regional Joint Board Files 5619/012: ACTWU Company Files 5619/013: ACTWU Research Department Correspondence Chronological Files 5619/014: ACWA Local 169 Files 5619/015: ACTWU Department of Occupational Safety and Health Files
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; UNITE HERE (Organization)
5675115
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, AFL-CIO, CLC: 1914-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  glass plate with gold lettering
- David Dubinsky's Fedora (Box 2, Folder 1)
- ACTWA - Baby Bib (Box 3, Folder 1)
- ACTWU - Badges, 1948-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- ACTWU - Badges, 1952-1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- ACTWU - Badges, 1950-1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Jacob S. Potofsky - Label (Box 3, Folder 5)
- ACTWU - Badges, Buttons, Push-Pins, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Badges, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Badges, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- ACTWU - T-Shirt (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America & ACTWU - Misc. Memorabilia (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Key chains; Clinton/Gore buttons; cloth clothing labels; ball point pens, note pad; Staff name badge
- ACTWU (Box 3, Folder 11)
  templates for advertising
- Miscellaneous Memorabilia, 1922-1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Gold coin (1922); cuff links; Gen. President Badge (1946); souvenir mini-portfolio from Twenty-Third biennial Convention, Atlantic City, N.J., May 14-18, 1982
- Misc. Memorabilia (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Stop Unfair Imports, T-Shirt; ACTWU tie (2); Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union AFL-CIO, CLC (business cards)
- Boys' Towns of Italy, Inc. - 35th Anniversary Award to Olga Diaz, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Sample Union Labels (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Amalgamated Bank of New York - Resolution (1979) (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Award of Appreciation presented to Olga Diaz - City of Hope, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- The Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee of the New York City Central Labor Council, AFL-CIO (1984) (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Boys' Towns of Italy, Inc. is proud to present the 35th Anniversary Award to Olga Diaz (1981) (Box 4, Folder 6)
- The Union Label & Service Trades of N.Y., AFL-CIO - Olga Diaz (1982) (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Golden Jubilee Convention, Vice President, badge; Membership Book - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Lincoln Centre Fellowship, Chicago (Invitation), 1913; Resolutions in Respect to the Service of John E. Williams 1919, 1913-1919 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Bessie Abramowitz Hillman (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Program and invitation from a Dinner and Dance in honor of the President and Mrs. Johnson (Jan. 13, 1969) (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Passport to Man and His World//passport Pour la Terre des Hommes Expo 67, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- 1920-1970 - International Supplement - Histadrut' s Anniversary. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- CIO Convention - October 31, 1949 - In Memoriam of Van Bittner (Box 5, Folder 4)
- City of Hope and National Medical Center - Commends Olga Diaz (Box 5, Folder 5)
- May Their Ideals Live Forever, In Their Spirit We Carry On - October 24, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Dept. of StateTo Certify that Miss Dorothy Bellancadesignated a Labor Adviser, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- CIO Memorial Statement for Sidney Hillman - July 18, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous Memorabilia, 1936-1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  1978 Calendar; 1984 Honor Roll; 40 Anos, Confederacion de Trabajadores de Venezuela, 1936-1976 (small banner); 15 Anos, 1961 Octubre 1976 (small flag); news paper ad (Daily News Record, June 12, 1979); news paper advertisement; Confederacion de Trab
- ACTWU Buttons - "Pay to the Order" Rubber Stamp (Box 6, Folder 1)
  11 buttons/pins transferred from 5619/034
- Advertisement drawings and ideas (Box 6, Folder 2)
  assortment of graphics
- Clinton/Gore // Dukakis/Bentsen Campaign buttons (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Farmworker stamps (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Press Badge from 28th Biennial Conv. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Paper "Dukakis" hat (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Rubber Stamps (Box 6, Folder 7)
  United Labor Service Agency; Pay to the order of The Amalgamated Bank of New York (2)
- No More Bandaids! Trans from 5619/023, National Health Insurance (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Sidney Hillman Mausoleum, Bronze Seal and Mausoleum marker (Box 7)
  - Sidney Hillman Mausoleum, Bronze Seal and Mausoleum Marker - Architecture drawings (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Louis Hollander and Vincent Lacapria (Box 8)
  - Sketch/portrait - Louis Hollander and Vincent Lacapria (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, Local 400; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Seal makers (2) (Box 9, Folder 1)
- New York Joint Board of the Amalgamated; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Seal makers (2) (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers of America - Seal makers - (2) (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers of America - Seal makers - (2) (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America - Seal makers (2) (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers of America (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Tanakh: The Holy Scriptures enclosed in a cedar box (Box 15, Folder 1)
- National Association for Puerto Rican Civil Rights, Inc. - Recognition Award - Olga Diaz (1980) (Box 16, Folder 1)
- NYSSILR - Extends Grateful Appreciation to: Olga Diaz, for valuable assistance in this special program - The Hispanic Labor Studies Program, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Otorga el Presente Certificado de Participacion a Olga Diaz, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Plastic sign - We Feature the Amalgamated Union Label (Box 16, Folder 4)